<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Coq | Yet Another Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/categories/coq/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-01T15:20:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daria Jung]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Re-learning Math With Coq]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/07/31/re-learning-math-with-coq/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T10:25:40-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/07/31/re-learning-math-with-coq</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last time I was doing a lot of inductive proofs was during my third year of high school. I did a few in my Discrete Mathematics class, but to be quite honest, I hardly remember anything from that it (I should really revisit the material at some point&hellip;).</p>

<p>Considering that it has been more than four years &mdash;I took a gap year between my second and third year of university, I am now going into third year&mdash; I was a bit unsure of my math chops. But working through <a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/sf/current/index.html">Software Foundations</a> has been an absolute blast. And it&rsquo;s been so cool to see the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Curry%E2%80%93Howard_correspondence">Curry-Howard correspondence</a> in action through writing proofs in Coq.</p>

<p>Rntz gave a great presentation on <a href="https://github.com/rntz/curry-howard-slides/raw/master/pres.pdf">Curry-Howard</a>, presenting formal logic, a lambda-calculus, and then showing the connection between formal logic proofs and typed expressions/programs.</p>

<p>So far, I&rsquo;ve been spending time proving some mathematical axioms such as the additive identity, multiplicative communtativity, right distributive property of multiplication over addition of numbers, and so on.</p>

<p>Coq has various proof tactics, <code>intros</code>, <code>destruct</code>, and <code>induction</code>, to name a few.</p>

<p>To show you the kind of stuff I&rsquo;ve been doing, let&rsquo;s work through an example.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s prove that <code>n + 0 = 0</code>.</p>

<p>First we define the theorem (adding a 0 to the right side of a natural number gives us the original natural number):</p>

<p><code>coq
Theorem plus_0_r : forall n:nat, n + 0 = n.
</code></p>

<p>So how do we prove this?</p>

<p>Well, first we need to introduce n into the scope of the proof.</p>

<p>```coq
Proof.</p>

<pre><code>intros.
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Coq shows us that we can now work with n, and that our subgoal is to prove that n + 0 = n.</p>

<p>```coq
1 subgoals, subgoal 1 (ID 88)</p>

<h1>n : nat</h1>

<p>n + 0 = n
```</p>

<p>Cool. And now we can induct on n. In induction, you must prove the base case of <code>n = 0</code>, and for <code>n = S n'</code>; <code>S n'</code> can be read as the <em>successor</em> of n', which is equivalent to n.</p>

<p>So now, we use the <code>induction</code> tactic in Coq:</p>

<p>```coq
Proof.</p>

<pre><code>intros. induction n as [| n'].
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now we have two subgoals to prove, the base case and the successor case:</p>

<p>```coq
2 subgoals, subgoal 1 (ID 91)</p>

<p>============================
0 + 0 = 0</p>

<p>subgoal 2 (ID 94) is:
S n' + 0 = S n'
```</p>

<p>For my own benefit, I like to write out what case I am proving, which in this case is for when <code>n = 0</code>.
As we see, Coq gives us <code>0 + 0 = 0</code>. We can simplify this expression by writing <code>simpl</code>, and Coq will reduce this to <code>0 = 0</code>. And we know <code>0 = 0</code>. It&rsquo;s a fact. We can simply write <code>reflexivity</code> to finish proving this subgoal.</p>

<p>As a sidenote, reflexivity will simplify for you, so it wasn&rsquo;t necessary to do the <code>simpl</code> step. However, I found it helps my thought process to write out all of the steps.</p>

<p>```coq
Proof.</p>

<pre><code>intros. induction n as [| n'].
Case "n = 0". simpl. reflexivity.
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Coq now tells us we have one subgoal remaining:</p>

<p>```coq
1 subgoals, subgoal 1 (ID 94)</p>

<p>n' : nat</p>

<h1>IHn' : n' + 0 = n'</h1>

<p>S n' + 0 = S n'
```</p>

<p>As you can see, we are given <code>IHn'</code>, an induction hypothesis to work with. So let&rsquo;s prove our second subgoal for case &ldquo;n = S n'&rdquo;:</p>

<p>We can simplify this down to <code>S (n' + 0) = S n</code> by using the <code>simpl</code> tactic. Adding a 0 to n', and then calling a successor on it is no different from adding 0 to the successor of n'.</p>

<p>```coq
1 subgoals, subgoal 1 (ID 101)</p>

<p>Case := &ldquo;n = S n'&rdquo; : String.string
n' : nat</p>

<h1>IHn' : n' + 0 = n'</h1>

<p>S (n' + 0) = S n'
```</p>

<p>But what&rsquo;s this? We have an induction hypothesis that tells us that <code>n' + 0 = n'</code>. Oh, this looks familiar. So let&rsquo;s rewrite <code>S (n' + 0)</code> using our induction hypothesis:</p>

<p>```coq
Proof.</p>

<pre><code>intros. induction n as [| n'].
Case "n = 0". simpl. reflexivity.
Case "n = S n'". simpl.  rewrite -&gt; IHn'.
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>```coq
1 subgoals, subgoal 1 (ID 102)</p>

<p>Case := &ldquo;n = S n'&rdquo; : String.string
n' : nat</p>

<h1>IHn' : n' + 0 = n'</h1>

<p>S n' = S n'
```</p>

<p>Omg, the left and the right are equivalent. And now we can say, this is true by reflexivity, and end our proof by writing <code>Qed.</code></p>

<p>Our full proof:</p>

<p>```coq
Proof.</p>

<pre><code>intros. induction n as [| n'].
Case "n = 0". simpl. reflexivity.
Case "n = S n'". simpl.  rewrite -&gt; IHn'. reflexivity.
</code></pre>

<p>Qed.
```</p>

<p>HOW COOL IS THAT???</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring Type Theory]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/07/28/exploring-type-theory/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-28T22:19:39-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/07/28/exploring-type-theory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started off today with a specific goal in mind. By the end of the day, I was pretty off my mark.</p>

<p>My original intent was to work through a tutorial, <a href="http://www.grabmueller.de/martin/www/pub/AlgorithmW.pdf">Algorithm W Step by Step</a>, for implementing the classic Algorithm W (proposed by Robin Milner) for type inference in Haskell. I was stoked to finally take a closer look at Hindley-Milner and foolishly thought I would spend a few days on it.</p>

<p>In reality, I had started my descent down the rabbit hole. I found myself reading, and while I felt comfortable with the actual Haskell code itself, the reasons for why the tutorial was implementing things by using sets, or talking about free type variables and type schemes made me feel that yeah, maybe(?) I could infer something from my understanding of Haskell, but I was still lacking appropriate knowledge for this literature.</p>

<p>So, I asked this silly question on Zulip:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>Stream Subject</strong>: Category Theory/Type Theory/Set Theory</p>

<p><strong>Message</strong>: Hi hi. I&rsquo;m delving into Hindley-Milner for type inference and I&rsquo;m finding lots of terminology that I don&rsquo;t understand. Are there any friendly introductions to all of the theories? AM I WAY IN OVER MY HEAD?</p></blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.rntz.net/">Rntz</a> pointed me to <a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/tapl/">Types and Programming Languages</a> as a resource and I was intrigued. I started reading it, and of course my attention started to wane because textbooks. After some googling, and remembering back to my first week at Hacker School, I was reminded of a UPenn grad course called <a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/sf/current/index.html">Software Foundations</a>. The course uses TAPL but also utilizes an interactive book of Coq proofs as its main text. Interactive? Sign me up.</p>

<p>Two ways to run Coq are through the CoqIDE or through Proof General Coq mode in Emacs. I found to my chagrin that CoqIDE was ugly and slow and in general, not something that I wanted to use. But that meant that I had to learn&hellip; Emacs. So for about two hours, I went through the Emacs tutorial and fiddled with my .emacs file, thinking about the time I saw Richard Stallman dressed as a saint from the Church of Emacs and resigned myself to learning a new text editor/operating system/whatever (plz don&rsquo;t hurt me, I&rsquo;m new to emacs).</p>

<p>After this, I couldn&rsquo;t figure out how to run Coq through Proof General, and time passed while I grew increasingly frustrated. Then Alan to the rescue! He helped me figure out that emacs wasn&rsquo;t correctly loading my path, and once that was fixed, I was able to write Coq and do cute stuff like:</p>

<p><code>coq
Proof. reflexivity. Qed.
</code></p>

<p>Yay!</p>

<p>Tomorrow I will continue working through Software Foundations. Aki, an alum, has also kindly pointed me to some resources for implementing type inference algorithms which I plan to hit up once I have gotten a feel for the theory behind it. Excited to see where this leads.</p>

<p>Oh, and I remapped <code>Caps Lock</code> from <code>ESC</code> to <code>CTRL</code>. So, uh, yeah.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
