<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Hacker School | Hacker School Log]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/categories/hacker-school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-18T19:12:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daria Jung]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School: Day 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-18T16:22:18-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/18/hacker-school-day-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I can&rsquo;t believe it has already been a week and a half at Hacker School. Wow. 12 weeks seems like a lot but the time is already flying by.</p>

<p>Today, I decided to resume my studies in Haskell. I worked on the week 11 assignment for Brent Yorgey&rsquo;s Haskell course. I continued working with the <code>Parser</code> data type, implementing some utilies and several new Parsers.</p>

<p>This is where I was introduced to <code>*&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;*</code> and the concept of lifting in functional programming (which I am still having a hard time fully understanding).</p>

<p>Described in the source for module <code>Control.Applicative</code> as:</p>

<p>```haskell
&mdash; | Sequence actions, discarding the value of the first argument.</p>

<pre><code>(*&gt;) :: f a -&gt; f b -&gt; f b
(*&gt;) = liftA2 (const id)
</code></pre>

<p>```
and</p>

<p>```haskell
&mdash; | Sequence actions, discarding the value of the second argument.</p>

<pre><code>(&lt;*) :: f a -&gt; f b -&gt; f a
(&lt;*) = liftA2 const
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Using some examples I worked out by hand:</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser (spaces *&gt; posInt) " 345"
</code></p>

<p>I understood this computation as first:</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser spaces " 345"
Just (" ", "345")
</code>
The <code>" "</code>, the result, is disregarded. We pass on &ldquo;345&rdquo; to the next call:</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser posInt "345"
Just (345, "")
</code></p>

<p>Since we are ignoring the result of <code>runParser spaces " 345"</code>, the final result is:</p>

<p><code>haskell
Just (345, "")
</code></p>

<p>Using the same inputs, but for <code>&lt;*</code> this time:</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser (spaces &lt;* posInt) " 345"
</code></p>

<p>First we run:</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser spaces " 345"
Just (" ", "345")
</code></p>

<p>This time, we <em>don&rsquo;t</em> disregard <code>" "</code>.</p>

<p>We pass on &ldquo;345&rdquo;:</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser posInt "345"
Just (345, "")
</code></p>

<p>Here we are ignoring <code>345</code>, the result of <code>runParser posInt "345"</code>.</p>

<p>The final result ends up being:</p>

<p><code>haskell
Just (" ", "")
</code>
Cool, how about one more.</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser (ident &lt;* posInt) "hello 345"
</code></p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser ident "hello 345"
Just ("hello", " 345")
</code></p>

<p>We keep <code>"hello"</code> and pass on <code>" 345"</code>.</p>

<p><code>haskell
ghci&gt; runParser posInt " 345"
Nothing
</code></p>

<p>Uh oh. We got <code>Nothing</code>. There is no state for us to use in the return <code>Maybe</code> tuple, so we end up with <code>Nothing</code>.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>posInt :: Parser Integer</code> : Checks for positive integers in String input.</li>
<li><code>spaces :: Parser String</code> : Checks for spaces in String input.</li>
<li><code>ident :: Parser String</code> : an identiﬁer can be any nonempty sequence of letters and digits, except that it may not start with a digit.</li>
</ul>


<p>I got this far in my understanding of these functions, but I still do not quite understand what is being &ldquo;lifted&rdquo; behind the scenes.</p>

<p>Lifting in the case of <code>(a -&gt; b) -&gt; f a -&gt; f b</code> is defined in LYaH as &ldquo;a function that takes a function and returns a new function that&rsquo;s just like the old one, only it takes a functor as a parameter and returns a functor as the result.&rdquo; I will mull this over more tonight, and perhaps ask Alan or some alumni in Zulip tomorrow if I am still having a hard time understanding the concept.</p>

<p>For about 30 minutes, I worked through the first six problems of <a href="http://www.haskell.org/haskellwiki/99_questions">99 Haskell Problems</a>. It&rsquo;s been pretty fun to revist things I learned a while back now that I am getting wrapped up in the intricacies of Haskell. My brain feels like it is exploding all the time.</p>

<p>Learning Haskell has been challenging. It is definitely rewarding, but there are many times when I feel discouraged because I don&rsquo;t know when I will understand things like Applicative Functors like the back of my hand. I often feel afraid that I <em>won&rsquo;t</em> ever understand these things, but then I tell myself, what&rsquo;s the rush?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School: Day 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/17/hacker-school-day-6/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T17:09:44-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/17/hacker-school-day-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I decided to take a mini break from Haskell (erm, I still did a wee bit of Haskell) and work on a one off project. I got in a bit early, around 9:30 am to finish up the <a href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/16/applicative-functors/">Applicative Functors</a> blog post. I was pretty impressed with how many Hacker Schoolers were already in at that point, and felt eager to start working.</p>

<p>The little bit of Haskell I did today was to implement an <code>Alternative</code> instance for a <code>Parser</code>.</p>

<p>If we remember from my previous blogpost, <code>Parser</code> is defined as such:</p>

<p><code>haskell
newtype Parser a = Parser { runParser :: String -&gt; Maybe (a, String) }
</code></p>

<p>The <code>Applicative Parser</code> instance is useful for making parsers of fixed and simple formats. Because we want to be able to handle
the concept of <em>choice</em>, we turn to the <code>Alternative</code> class.</p>

<p>The <code>Alternative</code> class is defined something like this:</p>

<p>```haskell
class Applicative f => Alternative f where</p>

<pre><code>empty :: f a
(&lt;|&gt;) :: f a -&gt; f a -&gt; f a
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>(&lt;|>) denotes a choice, so something like <code>p &lt;|&gt; q</code> means a choice between <code>p</code> or <code>q</code>.</p>

<p>So, my <code>Alternative</code> instance ended up being:</p>

<p>```haskell
instance Alternative Parser where</p>

<pre><code>empty = Parser $ const Nothing
p &lt;|&gt; q = Parser $ \s -&gt; runParser p s &lt;|&gt; runParser q s
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>An important hint here is that there is already an Alternative instance for Maybe:</p>

<p>```haskell
instance Alternative Maybe where</p>

<pre><code>empty = Nothing
Nothing &lt;|&gt; p = p
Just x &lt;|&gt; _ = Just x
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>This means that we can simply call <code>runParser p s</code> and <code>runParser q s</code>, which gives us Maybe tuples. We can then use (&lt;|>) from the <code>Alternative</code> instance of <code>Maybe</code> to choose between those two tuples and pass it to the Parser constructor.</p>

<p>If <code>runParser p s</code> succeeds, return its results, else try <code>runParser q s</code>. If that succeeds, return its results. Otherwise, a <code>Nothing</code> will be returned.</p>

<p>Pretty nifty!</p>

<p>The rest of today, I worked on a very simple <a href="https://github.com/dariajung/url_shortener">URL shortener</a>.</p>

<p>I found a tutorial online that used the md5 hashing algorithm and a base 64 encoding to generate a randomized string. The last five characters of this were taken, sanitized, and then used as the key for a key value store in Redis as well as a slug.</p>

<p>I whipped up a simple Flask app for 301 redirects from the shortened URL to the original URL. A quick lookup in Redis, and then a <code>return redirect(location, 301)</code> call did the trick.</p>

<p><code>http://blog.dariajung.com</code> results in <code>http://localhost:5000/iJp4fHs</code>. When I go to that URL, I am then redirected to my original URL.</p>

<p>The functionality is all very simple, so I don&rsquo;t check that the protocol identifier and such are in the URL. That might be for another day.</p>

<p>Overall, I think today was rather productive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Applicative Functors]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/16/applicative-functors/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T17:02:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/16/applicative-functors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today at Hacker School, I was studying functors and applicative functors in Haskell. Functors are structures that &ldquo;can be mapped over&rdquo; [1]. So, applicative functors are functors that allow functions to be applied <em>within</em> a functor. Functor-ception.</p>

<p>This concept proved to be a pretty difficult one for me to grasp today. I wrangled with it for several hours, reading and re-reading Learn You a Haskell&rsquo;s <a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/functors-applicative-functors-and-monoids">explanation</a> for them before I broke down and asked for help on the Haskell Zuplip thread. (Now I know that I should ask for help if I can&rsquo;t figure something out in 15 minutes on my own.)</p>

<p>The particular problem I was sweating over was writing an Applicative instance for a <code>Parser</code>:</p>

<p><code>haskell
newtype Parser a = Parser { runParser :: String -&gt; Maybe (a, String) }
</code></p>

<p>I was eventually able to come up with this:</p>

<p>```haskell
instance Applicative Parser where</p>

<pre><code>pure x = Parser $ \s -&gt; Just (x, s)
p &lt;*&gt; q = Parser $ \s -&gt;
        case (runParser p s) of 
            Nothing -&gt; Nothing
            Just (f, s') -&gt; case (runParser q s') of
                Nothing -&gt; Nothing
                Just (x, s'') -&gt; Just (f x, s'')
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Applicative instances have a <code>pure</code> method and a <code>&lt;*&gt;</code> method. <code>Pure</code> is simple enough. It has a type declaration of <code>pure :: a -&gt; f a</code>. Basically, it takes a value of any type, and returns that value wrapped in an applicative functor. Where I had trouble was implementing <code>&lt;*&gt;</code>. <code>&lt;*&gt;</code> has a type declaration of <code>f (a -&gt; b) -&gt; f a -&gt; f b</code>. Basically, it is like <code>fmap</code>, but it takes a functor with a function in it, and another functor. The function from the first functor is sort of mapped over the value in the second functor.</p>

<p>Chen, Hacker School W &lsquo;13, was a saint and guided me in grasping the intuition behind writing this applicative instance. <code>P</code> and <code>q</code> are both functors here. <code>P</code>, however, is the functor that holds a function within it. In order to apply this function to the second functor, he was able to explain to me that I needed to &ldquo;unwrap&rdquo; the each functor and pass each state on to the subsequent action. In this case, that would be to call <code>runParser</code> on the functor <code>p</code> and the first state <code>s</code>, which would return a type of <code>Maybe ((a-&gt;b), String)</code>. This is where the cases come in. The result of <code>runparser p s</code> could either be <code>Nothing</code> or <code>Just (f, s')</code>, where <code>f</code> is of type declaration <code>(a-&gt;b)</code> and <code>s'</code> is the second state. In the case of <code>Nothing</code>, we return <code>Nothing</code> because there is nothing to pass on to the second functor. On the other hand, we again run <code>runParser</code> to &ldquo;unwrap&rdquo; the second functor. Just as before, in the case of <code>Nothing</code>, we return <code>Nothing</code>. Otherwise, we get <code>Just (x, s'')</code>, where <code>x</code> is of type <code>a</code> and <code>s''</code> is the third state. With this, we can now apply <code>f</code> on <code>x</code> to go from something of type <code>a</code> to type <code>b</code>, and return the third state <code>s''</code>, resulting in <code>Just (f x, s'')</code>.</p>

<p>Whew. I definitely learned a ton doing this. I hope my explaination made sense!</p>

<p>Resources <br/>
[1] <a href="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Haskell/Applicative_Functors">Haskell/Applicative Functors</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School Week 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/15/hacker-school-week-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T18:20:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/15/hacker-school-week-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/hs_logo.png" alt="&quot;HS Logo&quot;" /></p>

<p>This past week was my first week at Hacker School, and I am finally getting around to setting up a blog!</p>

<p>I really haven&rsquo;t had much success with blogging in the past, so I am wondering how this is going to go, but I will try my best to write something everyday. The posts from my fellow batchmates have been very exciting to read, and have been a motivating factor for me to finally get Octopress set up.</p>

<p>Because I had already been working on a <a href="http://www.seas.upenn.edu/~cis194/lectures.html">course on Haskell</a> that I found online before Hacker School started, that was mainly what I focused on during my first week. The course is broken up into 12 lectures, with corresponding homework assignments. The amazing thing is, I was able to work through about one week&rsquo;s worth of material <em>per day</em>. It&rsquo;s incredible what can happen when you are learning for the sake of learning, with no worries that generally come from a work or school setting. If you had told me one year ago that I would be geeking out over Haskell, I would have laughed in your face. I would have thought that it was too academic, too hard of a language for someone like myself to learn. What I am finding though, is that once I commited myself to learning Haskell, once I was comfortable with the idea that I <em>too</em> was capable of learning Haskell, I started to have fun with the assignments.</p>

<p>The most recent assignment I worked on was with using the rose tree data structure from the <code>Data.Tree</code> library. Based on a tree of employees, where employees are given a name and a &ldquo;fun&rdquo; score, I was given the task of maximizing the fun score for a party and  returning its optimized guest list. The caveat is that if an employee&rsquo;s direct superior were also in attendance of the party, that employee wouldn&rsquo;t be able to have any fun, lowering their fun score to 0.</p>

<p>I think my road block for this assignment was implementing a fold function for the <code>tree</code> data type (to which I could pass a function that found the max fun score at each subtree later). I wasn&rsquo;t sure what the type signature for the fold should have been, which took up the most of my time. Once I got this function worked out, I was able to work through the rest of the assignment.</p>

<p>I wrote the fold as such:</p>

<p><code>haskell
treeFold :: (a -&gt; [b] -&gt; b) -&gt; Tree a -&gt; b
treeFold f tree = f (rootLabel tree) (map (treeFold f) (subForest tree))
</code></p>

<p>where <code>tree</code> is defined as</p>

<p>```haskell
 data Tree a = Node {</p>

<pre><code>rootLabel :: a, -- label value
subForest :: [Tree a] -- zero or more child trees
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>The <code>rootLabel</code> of the tree returns the element at that Node and then we map <code>treeFold f</code> to the subtrees of the Node, recursively calling <code>treeFold f</code> on the subtrees. These are then passed as parameters to the function <code>f</code>.</p>

<hr />

<p>Something else that I did last week was playing with Arduinos and Addressable LEDs (each pixel is individually programmable!). I bought an Arduino UNO a few years ago, and never had really done anything with it. Dana, a batchmate with lots of hardware experience, brought some addressable LEDs in for some of the Hacker Schoolers to play with.</p>

<p>The cool thing was that Adafruit already had a library called <a href="https://github.com/adafruit/Adafruit_NeoPixel">Adafruit NeoPixels</a> we could use, so we were able to just hook up the LEDs to the Arduino and we immediately saw a light show.</p>

<p><img src="/images/led.jpg" alt="&quot;HS Logo&quot;" /></p>

<p>We played around with making the LEDs blink, which we achieved by Mod-ing the number of LEDs, and then changing the RGB value to (0, 0, 0). It definitely distilled the fear of hardware many of us had once we understood how easy it was to get started with it with all of the resources online. I am totally obsessed with Adafruit now!</p>

<p>My hardware project that I would like to accomplish this summer is a temperature sensor that based on the serial output changes the colors of the addressable LEDs. If warm, the LEDs light up yellow/orange, if cool, a green color, etc.</p>

<p>I am loving Hacker School thus far. Well, love is a bit of an understatement.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
