<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | Hacker School Log]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-15T20:15:07-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daria Jung]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School: Days 11 &amp; 12]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/25/hacker-school-days-11-and-12/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T20:36:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/25/hacker-school-days-11-and-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m getting behind on my blogging, meep.</p>

<p>Day 11 recap:</p>

<ul>
<li>Spent half of the day trying to debug my sudoku solver&rsquo;s board parser, which was pretty difficult as everything type checked, but I was getting the wrong output.</li>
<li>Learned about the <a href="http://www.haskell.org/ghc/docs/latest/html/users_guide/ghci-debugger.html">GHCI interactive debugger</a>, which let me place break points and inspect variables where the execution of the program has stopped.</li>
<li>Alan gave me a quick overview of &ldquo;equational debugging&rdquo;, which is to test little snippets of your program and make sure that it is returning the right output.</li>
<li>I ended up pulling out more complicated bits of my code into smaller functions to make equational debugging more manageable.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day finishing up the sudoku solver. I debugged the constraint propagation aspect of the program, and then implemented the depth first search function which utilized the constraint propagation logic.</li>
</ul>


<p>Day 12 (today!), I decided to take (another) break from Haskell. I played around for most of the day with Paper.js, trying to make something beautiful, but eventually found that it didn&rsquo;t actually interest me too much. Around 3:00 pm, Stacy from Winter 2013 batch came by Hacker School to do a goal making workshop. It did really get me thinking about my time at Hacker School, and how I need to figure out when I can say that I have achieved my goal of being literate in Haskell. I think I will spend maybe a couple more weeks max on Haskell, and then switch over to Python. My main fear is that while Haskell is awesome, it isn&rsquo;t exactly a language that I will be able to work in once I become a professional software engineer.</p>

<p>After hitting a dead end with Paper.js, I decided to pivot and play around with Python. I implemented a simple echo server in Python, where the client will send back what the server sent to it. Then I got the idea to work on a GIF bot for Zulip because sometimes emoji just aren&rsquo;t enough :). You can ask gif bot &ldquo;gif me cats&rdquo; and an API query is sent to <a href="http://giphy.com/">Giphy</a>, and gif bot returns a gif that has been tagged with cats, in this example. It&rsquo;s basically done at this point, and works locally, but I&rsquo;m not sure what the protocol is for having a permanent presence from the bot. Do I serve it on AWS/Heroku? I think I will ask Allison tomorrow. I&rsquo;m also curious if I should demo this tomorrow afternoon.</p>

<p>Here is gif bot in action:</p>

<p><img src="/images/gifbot.png" alt="&quot;Gif Bot in action&quot;" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School: Days 9 &amp; 10]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/24/hacker-school-days-9-and-10/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-24T09:58:30-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/24/hacker-school-days-9-and-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I didn&rsquo;t get a chance to blog about last Friday (Day 9) so I&rsquo;ll do a quick recap:</p>

<ul>
<li>First day of interview prep.</li>
<li>Worked on <a href="https://hackpad.com/Manage-those-phone-books-wK1MycZ5ATb">Manage those Phonebooks</a> in Python.</li>
<li>Turns out I had a lot of trouble parsing command line inputs, so I spent a good chunk of time on that before I decided to come back to it at the end.</li>
<li>This exercise made me feel a bit uncomfortable about how well I know a language. I&rsquo;ve been spending all of my time on Haskell and haven&rsquo;t touched Java or Python in a while.</li>
<li>Continued reading about Monads.</li>
</ul>


<p>Yesterday (Day 10), we received new check-in groups. It seems that they rotate every two weeks, and I&rsquo;m enjoying that as it gives me the chance to interact with more of my fellow Hacker Schoolers in a smaller setting.</p>

<p>I spent a good chunk of the morning finishing up the last assignment from Brent Yorgey&rsquo;s Haskell course programming a Risk, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Risk_(game)" target="_blank">boardgame</a>, simulator. It was cool to play around with Random generators to simulate die rolls, and also to simulate 1000 invasions (repeated calls to battle until there are no defenders remaining, or fewer than two attackers left) of varying defending and attacking army sizes. This was encompassed in a Battlefield data type, where Battlefield is defined as:</p>

<p>```haskell
type Army = Int</p>

<p>data Battlefield = Battlefield</p>

<pre><code>               { attackers :: Army, defenders :: Army }
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>After this, I ended up stumbling on Peter Norvig&rsquo;s Sudoku solver <a href="http://norvig.com/sudoku.html">paper</a> and decided to implement it in Haskell. I&rsquo;ve been struggling through lots of type errors but I was surprised and happy to find that I got so engrossed in my task that I stayed at Hacker School for almost 12 hours yesterday. It&rsquo;s really neat to be this absorbed in something, and feeling myself gain more confidence through being challenged by my own curiosities. Once I finish this up, I will definitely be needing some code review.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School: Day 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/17/hacker-school-day-6/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-17T17:09:44-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/17/hacker-school-day-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, I decided to take a mini break from Haskell (erm, I still did a wee bit of Haskell) and work on a one off project. I got in a bit early, around 9:30 am to finish up the <a href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/16/applicative-functors/">Applicative Functors</a> blog post. I was pretty impressed with how many Hacker Schoolers were already in at that point, and felt eager to start working.</p>

<p>The little bit of Haskell I did today was to implement an <code>Alternative</code> instance for a <code>Parser</code>.</p>

<p>If we remember from my previous blogpost, <code>Parser</code> is defined as such:</p>

<p><code>haskell
newtype Parser a = Parser { runParser :: String -&gt; Maybe (a, String) }
</code></p>

<p>The <code>Applicative Parser</code> instance is useful for making parsers of fixed and simple formats. Because we want to be able to handle
the concept of <em>choice</em>, we turn to the <code>Alternative</code> class.</p>

<p>The <code>Alternative</code> class is defined something like this:</p>

<p>```haskell
class Applicative f => Alternative f where</p>

<pre><code>empty :: f a
(&lt;|&gt;) :: f a -&gt; f a -&gt; f a
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>(&lt;|>) denotes a choice, so something like <code>p &lt;|&gt; q</code> means a choice between <code>p</code> or <code>q</code>.</p>

<p>So, my <code>Alternative</code> instance ended up being:</p>

<p>```haskell
instance Alternative Parser where</p>

<pre><code>empty = Parser $ const Nothing
p &lt;|&gt; q = Parser $ \s -&gt; runParser p s &lt;|&gt; runParser q s
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>An important hint here is that there is already an Alternative instance for Maybe:</p>

<p>```haskell
instance Alternative Maybe where</p>

<pre><code>empty = Nothing
Nothing &lt;|&gt; p = p
Just x &lt;|&gt; _ = Just x
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>This means that we can simply call <code>runParser p s</code> and <code>runParser q s</code>, which gives us Maybe tuples. We can then use (&lt;|>) from the <code>Alternative</code> instance of <code>Maybe</code> to choose between those two tuples and pass it to the Parser constructor.</p>

<p>If <code>runParser p s</code> succeeds, return its results, else try <code>runParser q s</code>. If that succeeds, return its results. Otherwise, a <code>Nothing</code> will be returned.</p>

<p>Pretty nifty!</p>

<p>The rest of today, I worked on a very simple <a href="https://github.com/dariajung/url_shortener">URL shortener</a>.</p>

<p>I found a tutorial online that used the md5 hashing algorithm and a base 64 encoding to generate a randomized string. The last five characters of this were taken, sanitized, and then used as the key for a key value store in Redis as well as a slug.</p>

<p>I whipped up a simple Flask app for 301 redirects from the shortened URL to the original URL. A quick lookup in Redis, and then a <code>return redirect(location, 301)</code> call did the trick.</p>

<p><code>http://blog.dariajung.com</code> results in <code>http://localhost:5000/iJp4fHs</code>. When I go to that URL, I am then redirected to my original URL.</p>

<p>The functionality is all very simple, so I don&rsquo;t check that the protocol identifier and such are in the URL. That might be for another day.</p>

<p>Overall, I think today was rather productive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
