<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bot | Yet Another Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/categories/bot/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-12T17:41:45-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Daria Jung]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hacker School: Days 11 &amp; 12]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/25/hacker-school-days-11-and-12/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-25T20:36:12-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.dariajung.com/blog/2014/06/25/hacker-school-days-11-and-12</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m getting behind on my blogging, meep.</p>

<p>Day 11 recap:</p>

<ul>
<li>Spent half of the day trying to debug my sudoku solver&rsquo;s board parser, which was pretty difficult as everything type checked, but I was getting the wrong output.</li>
<li>Learned about the <a href="http://www.haskell.org/ghc/docs/latest/html/users_guide/ghci-debugger.html">GHCI interactive debugger</a>, which let me place break points and inspect variables where the execution of the program has stopped.</li>
<li>Alan gave me a quick overview of &ldquo;equational debugging&rdquo;, which is to test little snippets of your program and make sure that it is returning the right output.</li>
<li>I ended up pulling out more complicated bits of my code into smaller functions to make equational debugging more manageable.</li>
<li>Spent the rest of the day finishing up the sudoku solver. I debugged the constraint propagation aspect of the program, and then implemented the depth first search function which utilized the constraint propagation logic.</li>
</ul>


<p>Day 12 (today!), I decided to take (another) break from Haskell. I played around for most of the day with Paper.js, trying to make something beautiful, but eventually found that it didn&rsquo;t actually interest me too much. Around 3:00 pm, Stacy from Winter 2013 batch came by Hacker School to do a goal making workshop. It did really get me thinking about my time at Hacker School, and how I need to figure out when I can say that I have achieved my goal of being literate in Haskell. I think I will spend maybe a couple more weeks max on Haskell, and then switch over to Python. My main fear is that while Haskell is awesome, it isn&rsquo;t exactly a language that I will be able to work in once I become a professional software engineer.</p>

<p>After hitting a dead end with Paper.js, I decided to pivot and play around with Python. I implemented a simple echo server in Python, where the client will send back what the server sent to it. Then I got the idea to work on a GIF bot for Zulip because sometimes emoji just aren&rsquo;t enough :). You can ask gif bot &ldquo;gif me cats&rdquo; and an API query is sent to <a href="http://giphy.com/">Giphy</a>, and gif bot returns a gif that has been tagged with cats, in this example. It&rsquo;s basically done at this point, and works locally, but I&rsquo;m not sure what the protocol is for having a permanent presence from the bot. Do I serve it on AWS/Heroku? I think I will ask Allison tomorrow. I&rsquo;m also curious if I should demo this tomorrow afternoon.</p>

<p>Here is gif bot in action:</p>

<p><img src="/images/gifbot.png" alt="&quot;Gif Bot in action&quot;" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
